Welcome to this course focused on getting started with
Добро пожаловать на курс, посвящённый первым шагам в Model Context Protocol.
model context protocol. My name is Stephen Grider
Меня зовут Стивен Грайдер,
and I'll be guiding you through everything you need to know around MCP.
и я помогу вам разобраться во всём, что нужно знать об MCP.
Let's first begin by understanding exactly what we'll cover in
Сначала разберёмся, что именно мы будем изучать в
the coming videos. We'll first get an overview
предстоящих уроках. Мы получим обзор
on MCP and understand what problems it is intended
MCP и поймём, какие задачи он помогает решать.
to solve. We'll then start to look at the basics
Затем перейдём к основам архитектуры MCP,
of MCP architecture by covering the responsibilities
разберём обязанности клиентов и серверов MCP.
of MCP clients and servers. Then
Потом рассмотрим три базовых компонента
it is on to the three basic components of an MCP
MCP-сервера. Сначала вспомним о тулзах,
server. First, we'll look at tools, which are intended
которые потребляют языковые модели.
to be consumed by language models. After
Далее поговорим о ресурсах, которые позволяют
that, we'll study resources, which allow a server to
серверу делиться данными с клиентами.
share data with clients. And finally, prompts,
И в конце обсудим промпты,
which will provide tune directions to language
дающие модельным подсказки для работы.
models. Now there's a lot of content for
Контента много, поэтому есть требования
us to get through, so there are a couple of requirements on
для вас. Первое — базовые знания Python.
your side. First, you need to have some basic Python
Второе — мы будем писать код,
knowledge. Second, we will be writing out some code,
и для этого нужна локальная установка Python.
and this will require a local Python installation. We
Проект будем вести через CLI UV.
will be managing our project with the UV CLI.
Если он у вас не установлен, скачайте его заранее.
And if you don't have it installed, I recommend grabbing it now. I'll
Ссылку вы увидите на экране.